<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" version="2.0"><channel><title>Big Yang Theory</title><description>Math, Code, &amp; Everything in Between</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.7</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 06:08:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Uncertainty &amp; Approximation - Physical &amp; Ephemeral</title><description>&lt;p&gt;No man has ever drawn a perfect circle, no metal beam ever made has been perfectly straight - no point drawn has ever been zero dimensional, and no sphere ever truly spherical.  We strive for predictability and determinism, yet we live in a reality that is inherently uncertain and indeterminate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/uncertainty-approximation-physical-ephemeral/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">80d4ffd3-b143-4051-b8cb-8c26671ac185</guid><dc:creator>Jeffrey Yang</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2015 04:24:29 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;No man has ever drawn a perfect circle, no metal beam ever made has been perfectly straight - no point drawn has ever been zero dimensional, and no sphere ever truly spherical.  We strive for predictability and determinism, yet we live in a reality that is inherently uncertain and indeterminate.  If there is a message in this post, which there may or may be not, it would be that the only certainty - is that there will always be uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;99.999...% of all problems ever encountered in the physical sciences (in fact, in any discipline) are not exactly solvable.  We are raised in an environment within which infinite precision is impossible, yet we are led to believe it is attainable. Unless you were educated in an accelerated or advanced high school program, you've probably never truly internalized this concept until attending college level quantitative science courses (I know I didn't).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this current context, I am specifically referring to the inability to solve for a variable(s) in your equation exactly.  Take, for example, calculating the necessary curvature for an airplane wing to achieve a certain amount of lift under certain conditions.  This calculation inherently relies on the number Pi, and Pi itself is an irrational number (in fact, a transcendental number) - that is, it has infinitely non-repeating decimal places.  This means that your calculation of the curvature of the wing will only ever be solved to as many significant digits as you have used in your implementation of Pi in the equation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is only a consideration on a mathematical level.  A similar degree of uncertainty arises on a computational level.  Hopefully you're using a computer to do these calculations, but you're computer itself has an inherent degree of granularity hard-coded within its ability to perform calculations.  This includes the fact that there is a limited set of numbers your computer can use constrained by the number of possible bits allocated for a number type (I may be fudging some terms here - but the message is there).  This also includes how your computer traverses a continuous set - say, the number line between 0 and 1.  Ultimately, there's a discreteness introduced into what is otherwise a supposed continuous process due to the fact that there is a limited set of numbers a computer has available to itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uncertainty in this form is so prevalent in all fields in the physical sciences that there are whole disciplines and numerous methods devoted specifically to address the problem.  Disciplines like Numerical Analysis and methods such as Perturbation Theory are are, by design, meant to expedite approximations so that they can be computed faster and with more certainty (numerical analysis) - and, in fact, to give us at least some approach to solving for something that cannot be exactly solved for (perturbative methods).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now want to revisit the concept of mathematical uncertainty that I touched upon earlier.  If you were to draw a line segment and label one end 0 and the other end 100, and you were then to, say, throw a dart which hits a point on said line.  You have a 0% chance of hitting a whole number.  In fact you have a 0% chance of hitting even a rational number.  MOREOVER, you have a 0% chance of hitting even an algebraic number (algebraic numbers encompass even irrational numbers such as the square root of 2 because it can be written as the solution to an algebraic equation - that is x^2 = 2).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The set of whole numbers, rational numbers, and algebraic numbers has a size of infinity.  The size of the set of all real numbers also has a size of infinity.  But the size of the set or real numbers is, in a sense, so much more infinite than the size of whole/rational numbers (google 'continuum hypothesis').  The point is, just as how almost all equations cannot be solved for exactly, the same is true of numbers.  'Almost All' (this is a true mathematical condition, almost all, wiki it) numbers are transcendental.  They cannot be expressed as the solution to some finite equation.  They cannot be computed to infinite precision within finite time.  And this is not a physical concept we are referring to.  We are referring to the concept of numbers!  We are referring to something that exists only in the mind!  Yet even that cannot be determined to infinite precision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The uneasiness about this idea was contemplated as far back as the ancient Greeks (probably even farther).  The discovery of irrational numbers is usually attributed to Hippasus, who belonged to a group called the Pythagoreans.  The Pythagoreans were a sect who followed the teachings of Pythagoras influenced mostly via a study of astronomy, mathematics, and music.  It is said that when Hippasus brought to light his discovery of irrational numbers at sea, his fellow compatriots threw him overboard "...for having produced an element in the universe which denied the...doctrine that all phenomena in the universe can be reduced to whole numbers and their ratios."&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you've made it this far, congratulations, you've basically just had me fart into your ears for the last 5 minutes.  I'd like to say more, but this can go on forever (maybe in another blog post).  Cherish the moments you have, cherish the ones you love, cherish the time you spend with one another.  Their fate is as uncertain as your own.  The only thing certain, is uncertainty itself - the only constant, is change itself.  And now I go back to coding.  As always - stay happy, stay strong, stay passionate - and take care of yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title>MakerSquare vs US Model of Education</title><description>&lt;p&gt;So I've just started my program at MakerSquare, one and a half weeks in, and it has already been one of the best experience of my life.  MakerSquare is a "Tech Bootcamp", a class that seeks to teach you the fundamentals of some form of programming (generally web-related) within the&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/makersquare-vs-u-s-model-of-education/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">2b5914c3-d026-458b-9d1d-e9e24a8b38c0</guid><dc:creator>Jeffrey Yang</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 15 Oct 2015 14:33:18 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;So I've just started my program at MakerSquare, one and a half weeks in, and it has already been one of the best experience of my life.  MakerSquare is a "Tech Bootcamp", a class that seeks to teach you the fundamentals of some form of programming (generally web-related) within the span of a few months such that you can apply for a job in said field right after you graduate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tech bootcamp programs tend to last roughly 3-4 months and the issue they seek to address is to produce truly useful individuals for the real world in software engineering upon graduation.  The reason this is even an issue is because most colleges/universities teach "Computer Science" (a.k.a. CS) but they do not have a program for "Software Engineering". They teach the theoretical framework of programming but they do not emphasize the applicability.  It's like teaching music theory, but never encouraging/training students to compose songs. And then sending students out into the field who may have a solid understanding of theory, but no idea how to compose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Face it, you are going to encounter challenges along the way when you are trying to create something new from scratch. And that is where colleges fail and "Trade Schools" succeed - that is what MakerSquare is, a trade school. You are learning one skill - software engineering in this case, and the entire course is focused on achieving proficiency and real-world applicability in this one skill. And this is where I will now segue into my critique of the educational model of the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am enjoying MakerSquare so much right now because, never have I been in an environment where everyone wants to be here. And by everyone, I mean students, instructors, and staff.  Students are all required to be within the premises 11 hours a day Mon-Fri and 8 and a half hours on Sat. It's called a bootcamp for a reason. Think about standard schools elementary through college - 75-90% of the students hate it and are only there because their parents force them or because it's what they feel is expected of them via social pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the real amazing thing about MakerSquare is, everyone WANTS to be here. The vibe is insane. Students, Staff, and Instructors regularly stay 12+ hours because they WANT to be here - they WANT to learn, they WANT to facilitate, they WANT to teach (respectively).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been an instructor for as many as 15 students at a time (taught courses in SAT math, AP calculus, AP physics, etc.) and I've been a student (obviously). I've seen both sides of the spectrum and MakerSquare is unique because this is the first time I've been in a class where EVERYONE wants to be here and EVERYONE wants to try their best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which leads me to my next point - that the US's model of education is extremely outdated. Throughout history, the most successful individuals (in terms of their contribution/improvement to society as a whole) made their most influential discoveries between the ages of 16-25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And, yet, in the U.S. educational model, we expect/enforce our citizens to - finish high school -&gt; go to college -&gt; ??? - &gt; profit (get job).  Basically, we take people at the prime of their lives, and place them into an institution where they sit on their asses and listen to some dude lecture, and then they go home and recite the lecture on paper (homework). Like, what is the point?  This is the time when one should get their hands dirty, to have some real hands-on experience, and yet they are just taking rote memorization classes. Even worse, half or more of the classes are GE's (general education) and are completely unrelated to the major one chose when he/she applied for said college.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the educational model of the progressive countries in the EU (European Union). In countries like Germany, Denmark, and the Netherlands - they actually discourage students from attending university. Not only that, their high school ends at grade 10 or 11 wherein students either go directly into the work force, take part in some form of apprenticeship, or attend a trade school (see where I'm getting at). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These progressive countries in the EU realize that a person should only enroll in university if he/she truly wants to work in academia and research.  University is essentially a trade school for becoming either a researcher or professor (usually both). Off topic tangent - I do not know what it's like in the countries I'm promoting, but it's hilarious that most universities in America require their researchers to teach courses.  It's stupid because some people are amazing at research but terrible at teaching, maybe because they are just inherently bad at it, but mostly because they just don't care much for it. So now you just have some dude/dudette giving a half-assed lecture because he/she just wants to get back to his/her actual job - researching. And this negative feedback of a brilliant researcher giving a crap lecture goes on to instill a lack of interest in the students attending said lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One final thought. I had a friend bring up an interesting point when I discussed this viewpoint of mine. That the countries in the EU adopt a rather Socialist system whereas the US is obviously Capitalist. His opinion is that there is less chance to "make it big" in the EU than in the US. But having thought more about it, I am still very much against the US's educational model/policies. I've just bagged on how American universities force their researchers to teach whether they want to or not. But consider our lower level educators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you're an American, you must by now have realized that the profession of teaching (from elementary through high school) in the US is extremely looked down upon. And why is that? We look down on the people who are the ones in charge of educating the next generation so we can improve ourselves as a species. It's ludicrous. In the progressive countries in the EU, teaching is a highly respected profession and teachers are paid extremely well so people who are geared towards being and educator are incentivized to go into the field.  But in the US, we scoff and laugh at our educators as the 'dumb ones' who couldn't get a job in some field and instead had to teach 'uneducated children'.  Once again, a negative feedback loop that just makes things worse and worse.  Low pay and lack of respect means the people who become teachers in the US tend, to be frank, to suck a lot. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reinforce this point, I was a physics major in university in the US, and there were several tracks you could take - BioPhysics, Mathematical Physics, AstroPhysics, and finally Physics Education - that is, becoming a physics/science teacher for schools below the college level. And the lowest caliber students ended up doing the Physics Education track because it was the easiest.  So basically, the worst students took up the role of being the ones to teach the next generation of students...think about that...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I've gone on for a bit too long - back to MakerSquare and coding until my brain won't work anymore. Stay strong, stay happy, stay passionate - and take care of yourselves.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>